Guide to the William Paul Wreden collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Paul Wreden Collection
1772-1918
MS 564
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
The collection consists of approximately two hundred letters and several other documents, most signed by English political figures and authors of the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.
Wreden, William P., 1910-1995
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William P. Wreden, 1961.
Scope and Contents
These papers consist of an autograph collection composed of over two hundred letters and a few other documents, most signed by English political figures and authors of the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. The materials have been arranged in alphabetical order.
Biographical / Historical
William P. Wreden was a rare book dealer and publisher. He entered the rare book business in 1937, and was also the owner of Pinole Land & Cattle Company, California. He published Bibliography of Valentine Greatrakes.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Europe; Great Britain; Autographs (manuscripts)
- Inventory, 1772-1918; 0.25; (1 box)
  - Adderly, James, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alcock, Sir Rutherford, 1809-1897, 1882 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alexander, Annie H. (Mrs. William), 1891 September 19 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alexander, William, abp. of Armagh, 1824-1911, 1893 September 23 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alford, Henry, 1810-1871, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alverstone, Richard Everard Webster, viscount, 1842-1915, 1892 February 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anglesey, Henry William Paget, first marquis of, 1768-1854, 1826 March 16, 1833 February 20, 1840 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ardagh, Sir John Charles, 1840-1907, 1872 January 3, 1883 August 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Argyll, George Douglas Campbell, eighth duke of, 1823-1900, 1882 August 7, 1892 July 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Armstrong, [William George Armstrong, baron, 1810-1900?], 1893 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ashburton, William Bingham Baring, second baron, 1799-1864, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aubry, _____, 1905 July 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Austin, S, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Barthélemy-Saint-Hilaire, Jules, 1805-1895, 1887 June 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Boyle, Capt. Courtney, 1770-?, 1826 December 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brooke, Sir Arthur, 1772-1843, 1814 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brough, Robert Barnabas, 1828-1860, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Canning, George, 1770-1827, 1815 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Canrobert, Francois Certain, 1807-1895, 1855 January 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cardwell, Edward Cardwell, viscount, 1813-1886, 1855 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Carlisle, George William Frederick Howard, seventh earl of, 1802-1864, 1849 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Carpenter, Sir William Boyd, 1841-1918, 1914 February 21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cartwright, John, 1740-1824, 1808 July 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Champneys, Basil, 1842-1935, 1889 February 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chantry, M. A., Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chevalier, Michael, 1806-1879, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Childers, Hugh Culling Eardley, 1827-1896, 1878 February 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clarendon, George William Frederick Villiers, fourth earl of, 1800-1870, 1845 June 20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cleveland, earl of, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cobbe, Frances Power, 1822-1904, 1884 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Coleman, Edward T., Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Coleridge, John Duke Coleridge, first baron, 1820-1894, 1881 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Coleridge, Sir John Taylor, 1790-1876, [1864 June 7?] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Colomb, Philip Howard, 1831-1899, 1890 April 8 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Colquhoun, Archibald Campbell, d. 1820, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Conder, Claude Regnier, 1848-1910, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Conington, John, 1825-1869, 1863 September 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cotton, Sir Sydney J., 1792-1874, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Courtney, Leonard Henry Courtney, first baron, 1832-1918, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Creasy, Sir Edward Shepherd, 1812-1878, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cross, Richard Assheton Cross, first viscount, 1823-1914, 1878 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Currie, Philip H. Wodehouse, first baron, 1834-1906, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Delane, John Thaddeus, 1817-1879, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Douglas, Sir Howard, bart., 1776-1861, 1853 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Egremont, George O'Brien Wyndham, third earl of, 1751-1837, 1831 April 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Elgin, James Bruce, eighth earl of, 1811-1863, 1859 August 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ellicott, Charles John, bp. of Gloucester, 1819-1905, 1865 November 22 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Elliot, Sir Henry George, 1817-1907, 1903 October 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fisher, John Arbuthnot Fisher, baron, 1841-1920, 1908 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fitzhardinge, Maurice Frederick Berkeley, first baron, 1788-1867, 1857 November 23, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Follett, Sir William Webb, 1798-1845, 1826 March 7 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lake, Sir Henry Atwell, 1801-1881, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lamington, Alexander Dundas Cochrane-Baillie, first baron, 1816-1890, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lansdowne, Henry Petty-Fitzmaurice, third marquis of, 1780-1863, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lawson, Sir Wilfrid, second bart., 1829-1906, 1865 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Leslie, G. D., Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lewis, Sir George Cornewall, second bart., 1806-1863, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lewis, Lady Maria Therese, 1803-1865, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Liverpool, Robert Banks Jenkinson, second earl of, 1770-1828, 1817 July 31 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [Lock of Drylaw, Henry Brougham Lock, first baron, 1827-1900?], 1862 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Londonderry, Charles William (Vane) Stewart, third marquis of, 1778-1854, 1835 March 4 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Longley, Charles Thomas, abp. of Canterbury, 1794-1868, 1866 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lowther, James, 1840-1904, 1883 February 18 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Loyson, Charles Jean Marie ("Père Hyacinthe"), 1827-1912, 1888 July 26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lyall, Sir Alfred Comyn, 1835-1911, 1910 September 29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - MacQueen, James, 1778-1870 (8 ALS), 1868 June 18-1869 February 26 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Marsden, William, 1754-1836, 1826 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Merle d'Aubigne, Jean Henri, 1794-1872, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ouseley, Sir Gore, 1770-1844, 1840 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Panizzi, Sir Anthony, 1797-1879, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ralston, William R. Shedden, 1828-1889, 1874 April 4, 1879 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Rich, Sir Robert, 1714-1785, 1772 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ridley, Matthew White, first viscount, 1842-1904, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ritchie, Charles Thomson Ritchie, first, baron, 1838-1906, 1889 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Roberts, William Page, 1836-1928, 1889 March 17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Robinson, William, 1726-1803, 1784 January 11 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Roupell, William, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Rowse, Robin, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Roxburghe, Susan Ker, duchess of, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Roy, William, 1726-1790, 1774 September 9 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Runciman, Sir Walter, bart., 1847-1937, 1903 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Russell, Sir Charles, 1863-1928, 1890 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Russell, [John Russell, first earl of, 1792-1878?], 1850 March 28, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ryle, John Charles, bp. of Liverpool, 1816-, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Salisbury, Robert Arthur Talbot GascoyneCecil, third marquess of, 1830-1903, 1889 March 7, 1890 August 28 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sandhurst, Sir William Rose Mansfield, 1819-1876, 1875 April 11 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sherbrooke, Robert Lowe, first viscount, 1811-1892, 1870 November 16, 1873 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Smith, John Pye, 1774-1851, 1840 January 20, February 17 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Spencer, John Poyntz Spencer, fifth earl of, 1835-1910, 1884 October 23 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Stanley, Dorothy (Tennant), Lady, 1873 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stanmore, Arthur Hamilton-Gordon, first baron, 1829-1912, 1897 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stanton, Arthur Henry, 1839-1913, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stubbs, William, bp. of Oxford, 1825-1901 (10 ALS), 1889 March 11-1900 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Tait, Archibald Campbell, abp. of Canterbury, 1811-1882, 1861 March 15, 1873 March 19, 1882 January 23 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Tait, Catherine [(Spooner), 1819-1878?], 1857 August 31, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Tait, I., Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Taunton, Henry Labouchere, first baron, 1798-1869, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Taylor, Robert, 1784-1844, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Teck, Francis Paul Louis Alexander, duke of, 1870-1900, 1892 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Temple, abp. of Exeter, 1878 July 27, 1885 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Temple, Sir Richard Carnac, bart., 1850-1931, 1885 December 10, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Thom, John Hamilton, 1808-1894, 1888 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Thompson, Sir Ellande, 1874 September 7 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Thompson, William Hepworth, 1810-1886, 1868 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Thomson, William, abp. of York, 1819-1890, 1869 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tooke, John Horne, 1736-1812, 1807 September 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tredegar, [Godfrey Charles Morgan, first viscount, 1830-1913?], 1892 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Truro, Thomas Wilde, first baron, 1782-1855, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tulloch, John, 1823-1886, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Turner, Sharon, 1768-1847, 1837 November 29, 1838 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tweedmouth, Edward Majoribanks, second baron, 1849-1909, 1906 February 16 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Villiers, Charles Pelham, 1802-1898, 1881 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Warre, Edmond, 1837-1920, 1912 July 6 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Wellesley, Richard Colley Wellesley, marquis of, 1760-1842, 1801 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Wellington, [Henry Wellesley, third duke of, 1846-1900?], 1899 October 31 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Whipple, Henry Benjamin, 1822-1901, 1890 November 19 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - White, Sir George Stuart, 1835-1912, 1903 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Whitelocke, John, 1757-1833, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Wilson, Sir Arnold. Talbot, 1884-1940, 1912 April 28 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Wilson, Sir Robert Thomas, 1777-1849, 1832 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Winchester, John Paulet, fourteenth marquis of, 1801-1887, 1868 September 11 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Winthrop, Robert Charles, 1809-1905, 1881 March 31 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Wood, Sir Evelyn, 1838-1919 (23 ALS), 1883 October 16-1918 March 4, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Wood, Lady Mary Paulina (Southwell)(6 ALS), 1891 September 13-1892 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Woodford, Sir Alexander George, 1782-1870 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Wrangel, Ferdinand Petrovich, baron, 1796-1870, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 13)